To understand RAG, let's first get a stronger
understanding of Embeddings and SimilaritySearch.
At its core, an embeddings model transformsa string into a vector of a specific dimension orlength that is represented in an embedding space.
Within this space, the closer two vectors are,the more similar the
corresponding strings aresemantically.
Think of it like a map where wordsand
phrases are represented as locations.
Wordswith similar meanings cluster together,
reflectingtheir semantic relationships.
You may have seenone hot encoded vectors in a more conventionalML model, where the vector encodes discrete datavia ones and zeros.
These types of vectors arecalled sparse vectors.
While the embeddings we'lluse for RAG, in which all values in the vectorcontain a floating point number that encodes somemeaning,
are known as density vectors.
Embeddingsare produced by machine learning models akin tohow other ml models generate numeric forecastsor sentiment classifications.
We train them onlarge amounts of text data, enabling them tograsp the nuances of language and representthem in the embedding space.
One of the firstembeddings models used for these kinds of
taskswas called Words2Vec.
Today, there are a plethoraof embeddings models to choose from.
Here are afew prominent ones, along with the dimensionalityof their embeddings,
in the table on the slide.
Ada from OpenAI with a dimensionality of 1,536.
Embed v3 from Cohere with a dimensionalityof 1,024.
And all-MiniLM from Hugging Face with adimensionality of 384.
It's worth mentioningthat models with higher dimensional outputscan potentially capture more intricate semanticrelationships.
However, this benefit comes at thecost of storing these longer vectors.
We mentionedin the last video that embeddings only make sensein the context of other embeddings they arecompared with in the same space.
So now thatwe have embeddings, how do we leverage them?
Thisis where similarity search comes in.
It allows us tocalculate the degree of similarity between twoembeddings using mathematical operations likecosine similarity, inner product, or squared L2Norm.
Cosine similarity measures the angle betweenvectors,
focusing on their direction.
This is apopular go-to metric for text similarity,
whichwe'll be using in this course.
Inner productconsiders both direction and magnitude,
providing a more comprehensive measure ofsimilarity.
Do note that if the vectors beingcompared are all units of equal length,
then innerproduct and cosine similarity are basically thesame thing.
Squared Euclidean measures the straight
line distance between vectors, focusing on theirabsolute positions.
On the right of the slide, thereare visual representations of cosine similarity, inner product, or dot product, and Square Euclidean respectively,
along with their mathematical formulas.
However, comparing a query vector to every singlevector in a database to find similar ones wouldbe inefficient and time-consuming.
To addressthis, similarity search utilizes indexing,
whichgroups similar embeddings together,
enablingsearches to focus on smaller areas
where themost similar embeddings already exist.
Commonindexing techniques include inverted file indices
and hierarchical navigable small worlds.
We won'tcover the specifics but just know that they are both
ways of narrowing a similarity search
toonly the promising areas before computing thedistances.
As you might expect, storing massivevectors, computing distances between them, andindexing embeddings is a lot of work.
To providean easier way for developers to interact withembeddings vector databases have become animportant tool.
These databases handle thecomplexities of storage, retrieval, and querying,
so all we need to do is feed our data in theproper format and query the vector databasefor what we need.
There are so many popularvector databases today but for this course, we'llbe using Chroma, a lightweight and scalable open-source vector database.
Chroma is a great choicefor a variety of use cases, and interacting withit will give you the skills you need
to interactwith other vector databases in your AI journey.